<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Risk on Clarity</title>
    <link>https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/tags/risk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Risk on Clarity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/tags/risk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Add Volatility to Protect Your Portfolio From Extreme Events</title>
      <link>https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/post/kurtosis-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/post/kurtosis-post/</guid>
      <description>
        
          
            &lt;h4 id=&#34;we-can-go-beyond-the-traditional-covariance-matrix-when-building-a-portfolio&#34;&gt;We can go beyond the traditional covariance matrix when building a portfolio.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Financial price return distributions are not Gaussian. Extreme events occur far more often than predicted by the normal curve, and human behavior (particularly panic selling) amplifies downside moves, making the distribution of returns left-skewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During these extreme events, volatility measures spike. Therefore, adding volatility derivatives (futures, swaps, or even straddles and strangles) to your portfolio can help capture diversification benefits in the higher moments of the distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
          
          
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical arbitrage with macro-factors</title>
      <link>https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/post/macro-factor-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/post/macro-factor-model/</guid>
      <description>
        
          
            &lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-reduce-portfolio-drawdowns-using-macroeconomic-variables&#34;&gt;How to reduce portfolio drawdowns using macroeconomic variables&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I showed in my previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://lfpazevedo.github.io/linearsim/post/ibov-clusters/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;identifying&lt;/strong&gt; independent (orthogonal) factors is crucial for explaining variations in asset prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When dealing with portfolios containing dozens or even hundreds of assets, we must understand the potential risks our capital is exposed to, so we can either avoid them or bet on a specific scenario to adjust the portfolio’s risk-return as desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post, I&#39;ll show how adding macro-features can improve portfolio metrics, &lt;strong&gt;especially&lt;/strong&gt; drawdowns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
          
        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
